<sect1 id="change_log"><title>Change Log</title>
<sect2 id="version_1_0_0"><title>Version 1.0.0 (2002-03-14)</title>

<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Initial stable public release.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_0_1"><title>Version 1.0.1 (2002-03-15)</title>

<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Fixed completely broken global vacation
handling.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added test case for vacation handling to test
suite.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_1"><title>Version 1.1 (2002-05-27)</title>

<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para> Added some reports to the example file, so users
actually get a result of the TaskJuggler run.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> Support for later completion of task and resources
added. By writing 'supplement task &lt;ID&gt; { ... }' an already
defined task can be extended. So it's easier now to create a file
which contains the vacations for all resources separate from the
resource definition itself. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Extended expression parser to work on string type
values as well.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><link linkend="TYPE_LOGICALEXPRESSION"> logicalexpression
</link> for hidetask, rolluptask etc. can now contain functions as
well. Currently there is support for 'istask', 'isresource',
'isaccount', 'issubtaskof', 'contains', 'ismilestone'.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Moved the docs directory from TaskJuggler subdir to
topdir.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added feature list and change-log to the
documentation.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><link
linkend="PROPERTY_reference">property_reference</link> is now sorted in
alphabetical order.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added lots of missing attributes to <link
linkend="PROPERTY_htmlaccountreport"> htmlaccountreport </link>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added missing <link linkend="PROPERTY_export"> export </link>
report to documentation. Export reports can now contain the scheduled
tasks as well as the resource allocations.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>New keywords
<computeroutput>planbooking</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>actualbooking</computeroutput> to enter fixed bookings
of <link linkend="PROPERTY_resource">resources</link> in the resource
declaration.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added new example project to illustrate the use of
export in big projects that are split into sub projects.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>HTML comments in HTML report files are now using correct
syntax.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Partial fix for correct time zone handling.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Support for STDIN reading and STDOUT writing added. This can be
used when calling TaskJuggler from CGI scripts.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_2"><title>Version 1.2 (2002-06-17)</title>

<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Fixed sorting by ID for all HTML reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed bug in vacation handling. Vacations that started before
the project were silently ignored.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for <link
linkend="PROPERTY_taskattributes"> taskattributes </link> to <link
linkend="PROPERTY_export">export</link> report.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>XML Output changes: Basically the XML output is more
simple to parse, some values were added and corrected.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added a first simple TaskJuggler XML-output viewer for
KDE.  See ktjview/README for installation. Configure with KDE support
enabled.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Disabled ical support by introducing the HAVE_ICAL
switch in the code.  The switch is not yet configure supported, but
building with --with-kde-support should work now without failing on
missing libical.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Support for URLs in HTML reports added.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Legacy HTML elements have been removed from HTML reports.
TaskJuggler now creates pure HTML 4.0 code.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for insertion of raw HTML code into
reports. This can be achieved with <link
linkend="PROPERTY_rawhead"> rawhead </link> and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_rawtail"> rawtail </link>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for user defined style sheets in HTML
reports by using the <link linkend="PROPERTY_rawstylesheet">
rawstylesheet </link> attribute.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Strings can now be enclosed in either single or double
quotes. A single quoted string may contain double quotes and vice
versa.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Working hours can now be declared on project level.
This also determines if a day is considered a working day or
not.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>With <link linkend="PROPERTY_startbuffer"> startbuffer
</link> and <link linkend="PROPERTY_endbuffer"> endbuffer </link> you can
now specify that there might be some air left in a certain
task.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Remo's Gantt chart generators have been included in the
<filename>Contrib</filename> directory.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_3"><title>Version 1.3 (2002-07-30)</title>

<para> <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>This release features some bigger cleanup changes.
Some of them do break compatibility with older version of TaskJuggler.
While we try very hard to avoid such situations, we do prefer to have
a consistent and logical language. Since the TaskJuggler user base is
still comparatively small, we decided to break compatibility now
rather than later. The changes are fairly minor, so they won't affect
many users.  Please see further down for more details.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added Perl/Tk tool to view Gantt charts and other
project information.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added PERT-chart generator from Philippe
Midol-Monnet.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for shifts in <link
linkend="PROPERTY_shift_selection"> shift </link>
and task allocate shift.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed vim syntax highlighting. Some keywords were missing.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Export report had syntax bug when milestones were present.
Fixed.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed handling of week, month and year duration specifications.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><link linkend="PROPERTY_now">now</link> and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_timingresolution">timingresolution</link> are no
longer properties. They are now optional attributes of <link
linkend="PROPERTY_project">project</link>. They currently still work as
properties as well but a warning is issued and they will be removed in
the next major release.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><link
linkend="PROPERTY_dailyworkinghours">dailyworkinghours</link>
and <link linkend="PROPERTY_yearlyworkingdays"> yearlyworkingdays
</link> have
been implemented to allow the user for better control over the
conversion from working days to working hours.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for a <link
linkend="PROPERTY_select">select</link>
function for alternative resource allocations.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>All load values in HTML reports can now be scaled by
specifying a <link
linkend="PROPERTY_loadunit">loadunit</link>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Improved readability of scheduler error messages.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added new example project to the Examples directory to
illustrate how to create shift schedules with TaskJuggler.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed scheduler for working hours around midnight.
This bug affected shifts as well as general working hours.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Extended timezone support. TaskJuggler will now
operate properly when TZ environment variable is set.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_4"><title>Version 1.4 (2002-12-18)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Only export references to tasks which are exported in
the same report.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Allow supplements of tasks within task definitions.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Converted documentation to DocBook. We now have a much
nicer and more structured manual. A printable version is available as
well now.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed HTML code for bookedlight cells. Those were
rendered without background on some browsers.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for multi-level sorting in reports.
<link linkend="PROPERTY_sorttasks">sorttasks</link> and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_sortresources">sortresources</link> now
take multiple criteria.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Several bugs in the sorting direction code have been
fixed. <computeroutput>startup</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>startdown</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>endup</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>enddown</computeroutput> have been replaced by 
	<computeroutput>planstartup</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>planstartdown</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>planendup</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>planenddown</computeroutput>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The optional attribute <link
linkend="PROPERTY_taskprefix">taskprefix</link> has been added to <link
linkend="PROPERTY_include">include</link>. This allows other projects to be
added at arbitrary points in the task tree as sub
projects.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Include statements within tasks are no longer
supported. They lead to ambiguous interpretation of
certain attributes.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The optional attribute <link
linkend="PROPERTY_taskroot">taskroot</link> has been added to <link
linkend="PROPERTY_export">export</link>. This allows to export sub tasks of a
tasks to be exported as root-level tasks.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The project file reader has been made fully Unicode
aware. It is now possible to use non-ASCII characters in text strings
and comments.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Two new functions have been added for use in <link
linkend="TYPE_LOGICALEXPRESSION">logical expressions</link>.
<computeroutput>isplanallocated</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>isactualallocated</computeroutput> can be used to show
only resources that have been allocated to a certain project in a
given time frame.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Made week of year calculation ISO 8601:1988 and DIN
1355 compliant. This also affects the month and year correlation in
weekly reports. You can use the optional project attributes <link
linkend="PROPERTY_weekstartssunday"> weekstartssunday </link> and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_weekstartsmonday"> weekstartsmonday </link> to
specify whether you like to start you week on Sunday or
Monday.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Support for a <computeroutput>flags</computeroutput>
columns added to HTML reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Sub tasks do now inherit the dependencies of their
container tasks. Specifying dependencies after sub tasks is now
illegal since they would be only used for checking, but not for
scheduling.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The logic checker for task attributes has been
completely rewritten. Since it probably catches some more errors, you
might have to fix your project now. Such cases would have resulted in
wrong results anyhow. Lots of test cases have been added to the test
suite to validate the checker.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The error reporting has been drastically improved. The
messages should be more precise now and errors that are triggered by
other errors should be not so prominent anymore.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>A new report type has been added. <link
linkend="PROPERTY_htmlweeklycalendar"> htmlweeklycalendar</link> can be used to
generate weekly calendars.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The format of time specifications in HTML reports is
now configurable via <link linkend="PROPERTY_timeformat"> timeformat 
</link> and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_shorttimeformat">shorttimeformat</link></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The keyword <computeroutput> xmltaskreport
</computeroutput> is now deprecated. It has been replaced by <link
linkend="PROPERTY_xmlreport"> xmlreport </link>. The rest of the syntax
remains identical. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The tool <computeroutput> xml2gantt.pl </computeroutput>
has been renamed to <computeroutput> tjx2gantt </computeroutput> and
moved from the Contrib directory to the main directory. The tool
<computeroutput> xml2png </computeroutput> has been
removed.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Included new version 0.2.2 of TJ-Pert from
Philippe.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The load numbers on the bars of the HTML task and
resource reports can now be turned on and off using the <link
linkend="PROPERTY_barlabels"> barlabels </link>
attribute.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The HTML reports feature now 3 kind of index numbers.
The sequence number reflects the order of declaration in the project
files. The index is a logical order based on the hierarchy and other
attributes. The number is the index in the generated list. What used
to be the <computeroutput>no</computeroutput> <link
linkend="PROPERTY_columns">column</link> is now the
<computeroutput>index</computeroutput> column.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The sequence of properties in the project file can now
be used as sorting criteria as well. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist> </para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_4_1"><title>Version 1.4.1 (2003-02-24)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Another redo of the loop detector. Now checking tasks
not only forward, but also backwards. Insufficiently specified task
boundaries are no longer detected, since they are flagged with missing
start/end messages after the scheduler run.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The dependency loop detector can now be skipped with
the --nodepcheck command line option.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The dependency loop detector runs now significantly
faster for larger projects.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Broken HTML table when
<computeroutput>schedule</computeroutput> was used with
<computeroutput>showactual</computeroutput> fixed.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>HTML reports can now show a <link
linkend="PROPERTY_columns">column</link> with the completion
degree and the completion status. The rows can also be sorted by these
new columns.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The HTML and XML reports are now UTF8 encoded. This should
eliminate problems with languages that require non-latin1 character
sets.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Currency values in HTML reports are now always right
aligned.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>A bug in the handling of nested Resources and Shifts
has been found and fixed. The bug lead to wrong load values for all
nested resources. The bug was introduced between versions 1.2 and 1.3.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>If some container tasks could not be scheduled due to
problems with a sub task no error message was generated. This has been
fixed now.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed scheduling of container tasks, so that container
tasks with only milestones get properly scheduled.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Only export min/max start/end times when they were
explicitly specified and do no longer inherit project start/end times
for this purpose.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><link
linkend="PROPERTY_columns">htmlaccountreport</link> now supports
quarterly and yearly calendar columns.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed XML reports so that milestone end dates are
same as start dates.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_4_2"><title>Version 1.4.2 (2003-03-10)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Indentation for tree structure in HTML reports is now
done with cell margins. This should no longer look bad if the label
gets wrapped by the browser.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>HTML tables now use explicit head and body sections.
This should repeat the table header when printing HTML reports from
some browsers.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed segfault in XML report generation. Only plan
values are now exported in XML report.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Task scheduling is also set when a fixed <link
linkend="PROPERTY_start">start</link> or <link
linkend="PROPERTY_end">end</link> date is specified.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Better error reporting for syntax errors in macros.
The call stack with full arguments is included in the error message
now.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The cost column in HTML <link
linkend="PROPERTY_columns">task</link> or resource reports now
only contains cost. Support for a revenue and profit column has been
added.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Abbreviated month name are now encoded properly in
non-Latin1 languages as well.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Milestones in HTML calendars are now visible in text
browsers and printouts as well.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>New attribute <link
linkend="PROPERTY_reference">reference</link> added to
task.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_9_0_unstable"><title>Version 1.9.0-unstable (2003-06-25)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>A new HTML report type for status report has been
added. See <link linkend="PROPERTY_htmlstatusreport">htmlstatusreport</link>
for details.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>HTML reports are now a lot more flexible. New CSS
elements have being used and the table elements are customizable now.
See <link linkend="PROPERTY_columns">optional column
attributes</link> for details.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Support for <link
linkend="PROPERTY_extend">user-defined attributes</link> has been
added.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Resource allocations can now be made <link
linkend="PROPERTY_mandatory">mandatory</link>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The format of numbers and currency values can now be
specified with <link
linkend="PROPERTY_numberformat">numberformat</link> and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_currencyformat">currencyformat</link>. The old
keyword currencydigits has been deprecated.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>All reports have now support for daily, weekly,
monthly, quarterly and yearly calendars. Task lines now contain
Gantt-chart like bars.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>HTML reports got the additional columns
<computeroutput>hierarchno</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>hierarchindex</computeroutput>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Several new query functions and operators for <link
linkend="TYPE_LOGICALEXPRESSION">logical expressions</link> have been
added.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Scenario specific task attributes can now be prefixed
with the scenario ID followed by a colon. The attributes starting with
'plan' or 'actual' have been deprecated.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed the URLs for task and resource names in HTML reports.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Cost, revenue and profit values as well as effort
values are now indented in tree sorting mode for all HTML reports.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Length and duration tasks with resource
allocations are no longer trimmed to the first and last resource
allocation.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed rounding error in effort calculation that led to
the allocation of an extra time slot in some cases.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed wrong scheduling of tasks that had a length or
duration specified as hours or minutes.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>'length' based task now use the global working hours
and global vacation settings as a criteria of what is a working day.
The tasks now always end during working hours and not at
midnight.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>isplanallocated and isactualallocated had broken time
interval handling. This is fixed now.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><link
linkend="PROPERTY_workinghours">workinghours</link> and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_currency">currency</link> are no longer global
properties. They are now optional attributes of the project
property.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The scenario name is no longer displayed by default if
more than one scenario is included in a report. A column
<computeroutput>scenario</computeroutput> must be explicitly added if
the scenario name should be reported for each line. The attributes
'showactual' and 'hideplan' have been deprecated. The <link
linkend="PROPERTY_scenarios">scenarios</link> attribute now
controls which scenarios should be shown.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Container tasks in export reports no longer have fixed
start and end date if they have their sub tasks exported as
well.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><link linkend="PROPERTY_allocate">Resource
allocations</link> are now inherited from parent
tasks.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_9_1_unstable"><title>Version 1.9.1-unstable (2003-07-29)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>A new class of reports has been added. CSV reports
(Comma separated values) are useful to import TaskJuggler reports
into other productivity applications such as
spreadsheets. The new reports are called <link
linkend="PROPERTY_csvtaskreport">csvtaskreport</link>, <link
linkend="PROPERTY_csvresourcereport">csvresourcereport</link> and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_csvaccountreport">csvaccountreport</link>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>HTML Calendars have now a navigation aid. Moving a
mouse over a cell will show the date and task/resource id in the
browser status bar.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Background cells in HTML calendars are now merged.
This makes TaskJuggler report generation faster and reduces the size
of HTML report files.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <link linkend="PROPERTY_export">export report</link>
can now be a main project file as well.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>A new keyword for taskattributes of export reports has
been introduced. The keyword <computeroutput>all</computeroutput>
causes all supported task attributes to be exported.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Various speed improvements.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The broken milestone symbol in HTML calendars has been
fixed.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>HTML reports now have a black grid to separate the
cells. This enhances readability both on the screen and on printouts.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The functions for <link
linkend="TYPE_LOGICALEXPRESSION">Logical Expressions</link> are now using
capital letters to improve their readability. The all lowercase
versions are still supported, but the recommended versions are now the
ones with intermixed uppercase letters.
<computeroutput>isTaskOfProject</computeroutput> was added as new
query function.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The maximum allocation of a resource for a task is no
longer limited by default. <link
linkend="PROPERTY_maxeffort">maxeffort</link> now defaults to 0
(unlimited) instead of 1.0 (8 hours per day). To have the same
behaviour as in TaskJuggler 1.x version you need to specify
<computeroutput>maxeffort 1.0</computeroutput> before any resource
definition. This change was made since many users were confused when
after increasing the daily working hours resources were still only
allocated 8 hours per day.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_1_9_2_unstable"><title>Version 1.9.2-unstable (2003-09-05)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Support for new XML format has been added. The old
format is still supported. TJ can read both old and new format XML
files but will use the new XML format for output.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The property <link
linkend="PROPERTY_projectids">projectids</link> has been added. It is used in
export reports to declare all the project IDs that are used in the
report.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Resource booking periods can now overlap with off-duty
hours, vacation or other task assignments. This is controlled by the
<link linkend="PROPERTY_sloppy">sloppy</link> attribute.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Effort based tasks now correctly recognize if the
effort was partially specified with booking attributes. The effort is
no longer allocated on top of the bookings.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>You can now reference environment variables by
writing <literal>$(VAR)</literal> as a means to pass runtime
values to TaskJuggler.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Several inconsistencies and off-by-one errors with
respect to task end times have been fixed.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>TaskJuggler can now create 'make' compatible
dependency information.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The number of errors after which TaskJuggler stops
processing is now configurable via a command line
option.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_2_0_0"><title>Version 2.0.0 (2003-11-24)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Fixed completion coloring in HTML
reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed segfault in certain cases of inherited resource
allocations.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><link linkend="PROPERTY_macro">Macro names</link> in macro
calls can now be prefixed by a question mark to suppress warnings if
the macro is undefined.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Microsoft and MacOS text files are now read in
correctly.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Report cells can be left empty and URLs can be
omitted controlled by a logical expression. This is controlled by
<link linkend="PROPERTY_hidecelltext">hidecelltext</link>
and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_hidecellurl">hidecellurl</link>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>New functions isATask, isAResource and isAnAccount can
now be used in logical expressions.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>XML version 2 files are now compressed with
zlib.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="version_2_0_1"><title>Version 2.0.1 (2004-03-08)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Fixed handling of resource allocations with multiple
shift intervals.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed double-quoting of HTML special characters such
as umlauts.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added query function isDutyOf() to select tasks where
a certain resource has been assigned to.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The contents of XML reports can now be limited with
the usual filter mechanisms. Support for <link
linkend="PROPERTY_hideresource">hideresource</link>, <link
linkend="PROPERTY_hidetask">hidetask</link>, <link
linkend="PROPERTY_rollupresource">rollupresource</link> and <link
linkend="PROPERTY_rolluptask">rolluptask</link> has been added. Also
<link linkend="PROPERTY_scenarios">scenario filtering</link> was
implemented for XML reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Weekly, monthly, quarterly and yearly HTML reports now
have resource vacations as well. If the vacation fills the complete
report cell term, the cell has a yellow background.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixes for building TaskJuggler on FreeBSD
added.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><link linkend="PROPERTY_maxeffort">maxeffort</link>
and <link linkend="PROPERTY_load">load</link> have been replaced by
the far more flexible concept of <link
linkend="PROPERTY_limits">limits</link>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="Changelog_2_1_0"><title>Version 2.1.0 (2005-03-07)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>TaskJuggler now has a nice face. Beside the
commandline application <computeroutput>taskjuggler</computeroutput>,
you can now use <computeroutput>TaskJuggler</computeroutput> or
<computeroutput>ktjview2</computeroutput> as a graphical user
interface to enter and schedule your projects.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>New optimizer that achieves much better resource
selection resulting in shorter overall project times.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Passive resources like meeting rooms, machines and the
like, that do not contribute to the effort of a task can now be
modelled by setting their efficiency to 0.0.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added critical path analyser. Each task is rated and
the rating can be listed in the HTML and CSV report.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>New task state added. When a task is not finished by
the planned end date, it now marked as
<computeroutput>late</computeroutput>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Task dependency specifications (<link
linkend="PROPERTY_depends">depends</link> or <link
linkend="PROPERTY_precedes">precedes</link> can now have optional gap
specification. It is possible to specify the gap in calendar time
(<link linkend="PROPERTY_gapduration">gapduration</link>) or working
time (<link
linkend="PROPERTY_gaplength">gaplength</link>).</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The speed of report generation has been significantly
improved. This is especially true for reports that make use of filter
functions.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added <computeroutput>status</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>statusNote</computeroutput> to XML
reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added some missing properties to the documentation.
Mainly the sorting criterias were missing.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed a memory leak during XML report
generation.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed scheduling of nested task that had an external
dependency and an inherited start/end date.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Limits of resource allocations with multiple
alternatives are now correctly handled. The limits were applied to
each individual resource instead of to the whole
allocation.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The task priority is now always properly respected.
Due to a bug in the scheduling algorithm a heavy mixture of ALAP and
ASAP tasks with various levels of priorities, ALAP tasks were treated
more favorable then they should have been treated. This fix can
drastically reduce the scheduling speed when you have a heavy mixture
of ALAP and ASAP tasks with varying priorities.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The error checking and reporting of logical
expressions has been drastically improved.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The reports are now generated relative to their
definition file and no longer relative to the current working
directory where you started the program.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="Changelog_2_1_1"><title>Version 2.1.1 (2005-08-04)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>The code for the generation of iCal reports has been
revived again. iCal is a standard format to exchange data with
calendar applications such as KOrganizer.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The contents of export reports can now be customized
with the <link linkend="PROPERTY_properties">properties</link>
attribute. The report interval is customizable as well
now.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Add new chapter to manual that describes how to use
TaskJuggler as a project tracking tool.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The HTML version of the manual has now a new look and
many more syntax examples have been added to the property
reference.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The TaskJuggler editor now supports printing of
project files.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed build with GCC 4.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed build problems in the doc directory on Debian
Unstable and FC3.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>We are now using docbook-utils instead of docbook-toys
to generate the documentation.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Filtering resources and tasks in the TaskJuggler GUI
reports now always works properly.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed generation of reports with absolute file
names.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Make sure that all dates specified in project files
lie within the Unix time space. For technical reasons we need to limit
this to 1971-01-01 - 2035-01-01.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed some crashes related to out of project time
specifications.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Warnings about pre 2.0 deprecated syntax elements have
been converted to errors.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed sorting of task reports when not using the
default scenario as first scenario.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed projection scheduling mode. Tasks with bookings
equal or larger than the effort lead to scheduling
errors.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="Changelog_2_2_0"><title>Version 2.2.0 (2005-12-05)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>The two graphical front-ends that have been present in earlier
TaskJuggler releases have been merged into one new front-end. It's
called TaskJugglerUI. The <computeroutput>ktjview2</computeroutput>
and <computeroutput>TaskJuggler</computeroutput> executables are no
longer included. This was done also to avoid name clashes on
Windows/Cygwin.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The TaskJuggler user interface now supports printing
of high-quality task and resource reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Major usability improvements for the GUI. It's now
fully navigable by keyboard. The scaling/zooming of the Gantt chart
has been improved.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>HTML reports are now rendered with an embedded
browser instead of launching an external browser.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Export reports are now loaded into the editor when
selected in the report browser.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The GUI supports now multiple project
templates. The templates can be customized on loading to reflect the
current date.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added date picker to GUI editor. By pressing CTRL+D
the user can insert or change a date using the comfortable date picker
widget.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The GUI editor now supports search and replace over
all files.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The computation of completion degrees of container
task has been improved to produce more meaningful values for all
milestone or all effort tasks.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>To get Gantt and resource reports in the GUI the
column 'chart' must be specified. They are no longer displayed
automatically. This was done to have more consistency between the
printed version of the GUI reports and the other
reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The default separator for CSV files is now a semicolon
since this is what OpenOffice.org uses by default. But this can be
changed if needed.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The projection scheduling mode has been fixed and
extended. In strict mode bookings will be scheduled only after the
current date. In sloppy mode, bookings will also be scheduled prior to
the current date for tasks that have no bookings at
all. The modes can be set in the scenario definition.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed reporting of value 1,000 in US currency
format.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed reported task duration value in all report
types. Value was only correct when unit 'days' was
used.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed account reports which had summary lines that
were all 0. In HTML reports the summary columns were rendered all
black.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed detection of cyclic brother tasks. This caused
taskjuggler to go into a memory hogging endless loop.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed bug in priority handling. Under certain
circumstances resources were allocated to lower priority tasks even
though they should have been assigned to higher priority
tasks.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed critical bug that turned 'precedes' of parent
tasks into 'depends' of child tasks.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed cost accounting for non-working resources. They
were always accounted to 0.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="Changelog_2_3_0"><title>Version 2.3.0 (2006-09-05)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Added improved error checking for 'timezone'
attribute. Only values as determined by tools like tzselect are
allowed, e. g. "Europe/Berlin".</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The GUI GANTT chart now can highlight critical
pathes. See <link linkend="PROPERTY_minslackrate">minslackrate</link>
for details how to use the feature.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The htmlweeklycalendar has been reworked. It now only
list tasks if they are being worked on that day. A new attribute <link
linkend="PROPERTY_weekdays">weekdays</link> can be used to only show
some days of the week. This can be used to hide e. g.
weekdays.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>ICal reports now include events. The completion value
is now shown correctly and assigned resources are
included.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed handling of tasks that have 'precedes' and
'depends' attributes.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Single and double quoted strings may now contain
single or double quotes when escaped by a preceding
backslash.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed 'gaplength' and 'gapduration' handling for other
scenarios than the default one.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed 'duration' column in all reports. Values equal
or smaller than 24 hours were reported too high.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>No longer show dependency arrows in Gantt chart for
inherited dependencies.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Generate proper warning when bookings are assigned to
container tasks or milestones.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>It is now possible to book off-hour and vacation time
slots with 'booking' when the <link
linkend="PROPERTY_overtime">overtime</link> attribute is
used.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for a more compact way to specify
bookings. It's now possible to list multiple comma seperated time
intervals in a single booking statement.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fix build system so that kde-config is no longer
mandatory. This simplifies compiling on Windows/Cygwin and Qt-only
installs.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Speed improvements for the loop detector. Large
projects with many top-level tasks should be scheduled significantly
faster now.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>'start' and 'end' attributes specified for derived 
scenarios no longer cause accidental changes of the scheduling
direction. This guarantees that a task has always the same scheduling
direction in all scenarios.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for more compact workinghour
specifications. <computeroutput>workinghours mon - fri 8:00 -
15:00</computeroutput> as well as <computeroutput>workinghours mon,
sat, sun off</computeroutput> are now possible.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added man pages for taskjuggler and
TaskJugglerUI.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed infinite loop bug in critical path detectors.
With certain task dependencies TaskJuggler could get stuck forever
when processing the project.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed TaskJugglerUI crash when processing a project
with many runaway tasks.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Better fit of report interval for printed Gantt
charts.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed header of weekly and monthly CSV
reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>XML reports now use the gzip compressed version 2 XML
format by default.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Add check to forbid assigning account groups to
tasks.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added Turkish translations for
TaskJugglerUI.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="Changelog_2_3_1"><title>Version 2.3.1 (2007-01-30)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>Added support for automatic macros like
<computeroutput>now</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>projectstart</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>projectend</computeroutput>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added monthly calendar HTML report.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added <computeroutput>period</computeroutput> property
as a shortcut for the combined use of
<computeroutput>start</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>end</computeroutput>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added more details to the pop-up info for tasks and
resources in the UI.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for warnings and turned some
non-critical errors into warnings.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Improved scheduling performance for projects with
long dependency chains.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added new attribute
<computeroutput>purge</computeroutput> to clear inherited allocations 
and flags from a task or resource.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed complexity explosion in loop detector and
critical path analyzer. Larger projects that made heavy use of
inherited dependencies had an exponentially growing run time of these
components.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The threshold for the critical path detection now
defaults to 10%. All pathes that have less than 10% slack time will be
marked as critical.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed problem where editor tools were doubled when
"Open Recent" was used while editor was open. This also triggered a
crash on program exit.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed double headline problem in most HTML
reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed a bug in the coloring of tasks in HTML reports
that had a 'complete' specification.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed documenation for usage of sorting modes for
scenario specific columns in reports and make them work
properly.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Force <computeroutput>now</computeroutput> date to be
aligned to the timing resolution.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed a major bug in the handling of multiple
scenarios. Values were inherited from peer scenarios instead of their
parents.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>More meaningful error messages for some impossible
combinations of fixed start/end times and
dependencies.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>For technical reasons we had to limit the
timingresolution between 5 minutes and 1 hour. Larger resolutions
caused too many hazards in corner case situations.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed <computeroutput>gaplength</computeroutput> for
time units other than days.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Really hide all inherited dependency arrows in Gantt
chart.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fix several crashes when the user is viewing reports
in the UI after an unsuccessfull scheduling run.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fix sorting of tasks in interactive resource reports
and sorting of resources in interactive task
reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The resource reporting in htmlweeklycalendar reports
has been fixed. The report can now be used in task or resource
reporting mode. The default is the task reporting mode which is
closest to the previous behaviour.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed values of the revenue and profit column in
resource reports. Resources can never generate a revenue so the value
must always be 0.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed crash when printing resource reports from the UI
that had a <computeroutput>hierarchyindex</computeroutput>
column.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The completion degree of container tasks that have sub
tasks with and without resource allocations was reported as 0. This
has been replaced with "in progress" as the completion degree cannot be
calculated.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="Changelog_2_4_0"><title>Version 2.4.0 (Some Day)</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>

<listitem><para>The critical path detector has been rewritten to
reduce the complexity explosion that is triggered by lots of inherited
dependencies in combination with long dependency chains.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The default minimum slack rate has been changed to
5%.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added support for C++ style single line comments.
Comment lines can now start with // or #.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added a warning when the working hours do not align
with the timing resolution.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The booking statements in export reports now include a
<computeroutput>overtime 2</computeroutput> attribute. This avoids the
error messages when the scheduling was based on overtime bookings and
the export file is read-in again.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Added a <computeroutput>Generate all
Reports</computeroutput> option to the menu of the
GUI.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The sloppiness 3 for booking statements is no longer
supported. The booking statements are processed in no particular
order, so it's undefined which booking will actually get the resource
in a conflict.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Removed support for KoTrus database.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fix HTML generation for HTMLWeeklyCalendar when cells
are empty.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Properly report durations in printed
reports.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Many editorial fixes were applied to the
manual.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Properly handle Pacific/Auckland
DST.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed a number of memory leaks.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Removed namespace collision for resource and account
custom attributes and added support for user defined account
attributes in the code.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Make sure that files that have been modified on disk
while edited by the TaskJugglerUI are detected properly. Probably with
KDE 3.5.4 the behavior of the Kate library changed so that the test no
longer worked properly and modified files were not
detected.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed crash when non existant file was
included.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Detect usage of undefined macros again. Undefined
macros were silently ignored. This should only happen when the macro
name is prefixed with a questionmark in the macro call.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Properly report effort and load of group resources
that have children with an efficiency different than
0.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed a crash when an illegal date was specified in a
project file.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The XML reports now also include the
accounts.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed a rounding error that caused dependency gaps to
be one time slot short.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The commandline version now properly returns a
non-zero value if the report generation caused an
error.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed the reversed sorting order for resource specific
sorting criteria.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Add workaround for new bahviour of tzset function in
glibc 2.5.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Fixed off-by-one-slot bug for limits on allocations
with multiple resources.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
</sect1>
